Show me the computer that did it.
That's it. That's where the world's
largest reversible prime was found in
there.
Today, ready? Breaking math news. New
prime. It's not often we get a new
prime. Well, a new prime. It's a
record-breaking length of prime, but
only of a certain type of prime. And
it's the same type of prime as 1,21.
That is a prime number. We call it a
prime. But more than that, this is a
special type of prime. This is an M Herp
prime. And do you want to have a guess
what an EMURP or MER prime is?
>> Look, it says on the box, doesn't it?
>> It really does.
>> It's a prime backwards. There you are.
Very, very funny mathematicians. Well
done. Haha. It's a prime, which is a
prime in both directions. So the number
1 0 2 1 is also prime. So because the
digits forward and the digits backwards
are prime, it's an emote prime for prime
backwards. It's pretty special.
>> That's nice.
>> Also works for 1,193.
I looked a couple up just so I was
ready. Now you can see there's already
going to be some constraints on what
makes an EMP because it's got to be odd
beginning and end. Can't be five
beginning and end. So you you're going
to rule out a lot like being prime is
not super rare.
>> What about two?
>> Two.
>> Do you count two? I count two.
>> Yeah.
>> Two is the special prime.
>> So why it can be special in this regard
as well, isn't it?
>> That's the same forward and backwards.
>> Mhm.
>> All one digit primes primes. Anything
palendroic
palendroic prime. I I think to be emurp
you really it has to be not a palendrome
but stays prime both ways. I feel like
that's I think palendromes are their own
special thing. So I would say two is a
palmic prime but these these are
special. So anyway to complete that 3
911 is also prime. So you can check
that.
>> Nice.
>> Um and a record-breaking
emote prime was discovered.
It has 10,01
digits, beating the previous record of
10,07
digits.
>> So, four more.
>> Four more. Four more digits.
>> Okay.
>> It's not a lot. And would you believe I
have already memorized all 10,1 digits?
>> I I would believe that.
>> You
would believe that. And you believe it
for a very good reason that it's very
easy to memorize. It's So, originally I
was like, "Oh my goodness." uh massive
record-breaking emote prime and when I
got the news so the person Stefan who
found it emailed me to say found a new
prime and I'm like I love the fact I am
the lightning rod for people to email
when they discover new primes and I
happen to be in a van with alien of
number file fame we both got very
excited we're like how long would it
take to say it could you then reverse
you saying it to still say a prime
number yes and then we realized saying
it would be super boring. So, without
dragging it out any longer, let's have a
look at this new record-breaking prime.
>> Let's do it.
>> It is
>> Hey, what are you looking at? You said
you'd memorized it.
>> Let me rephrase that. Uh, I could
memorize it.
>> Okay,
>> let me show you the I'll show you the
number and you get the idea. It is 3
bill867,632,931*
10 to the power of 10,0001 plus one.
What you have here is 10 to the power of
10,0001 means a one followed by 10,01
zeros and then you multiply this on the
front. So what that ends up looking like
is 3 8 6 7 6 3 2 93 1. Then you start 00
0 dot dot dot dot dot zero's for day 0
0. But then the plus one comes in
clutch. Boom. So that actual stretch in
the middle there that is going to be uh
10,000 zeros.
That's the easiest bit to remember. So,
if you lock in these digits on the top
and then say zero 10,000 times and then
say one, you're done. The question now
is, well, hang on. It's got to be a
reversible prime. So, you just flip the
whole thing around. Now, you can write
it out the fancy way. So, the fancy way
is 10. So, now the 10,10,
so that's going to give us 1 followed by
10,10 zeros. So that's 10,011 digits
including that lead one which is the
record-breaking length. But then on the
end you add the reverse of this. So then
you add on 1 3 9 2 oops 3 6 7 6 8 3 and
that gives you your number. So, so just
to you know for complete that's now a
one followed by a 0 0 0 dot dot dot dot
dot 0 0 1 3 9 2 3 6 7 6 8 3 and done.
There you go.
>> Wow.
>> Isn't that special?
>> It's good.
>> Yeah.
>> Who uh how was this done? Who like was
it done with a I'm assuming it was done
with a computer.
>> It's done with a computer. So we have
talked about this many years ago on
number file um prime grid cuz not many
people do prime grid. I mean I do as I
speak. There is a computer in my office
that I built solely to run prime grid
and I used to have a server called
Calculus Prime which is very sadly was
decommissioned when I moved office. It
was getting very old and adding a
trivial amount of compute power these
days. And someone called Stefan got
involved in Prime Grid. Got very excited
about different types of primes.
Realized that maybe they could break the
record for emers. So they wrote their
own prime civ. So, it's a way of like
you use numbers that aren't primes to
kind of build up where all the primes
must be because all the multiples of the
previous primes get removed. You civ
them out. They wrote their own terrible
prime civ their words, not mine, in CC
code. And then they also used some of
the offthe-shelf prime
algorithms on Prime Grid. So, if you go
on Prime Grid, there's a page which is
basically excellent prime algorithms and
they picked two of those and used them
as well. And then they just started
searching. And this is a clever way of
doing it. So you search for different
combinations of these and then different
lengths of zeros and then just chuck a
one on the other end. And if you find
one that works this way around, you
whoop and you check it the other way
around. And these are nice compact ways
to to phrase them. You set that code
running. You wait a very long time. I
actually don't know how long Stefan was
waiting. And it spits out one of these
and you email it to me. That
seems to be the entire
journey. I thought about emailing Matt
right at the beginning. I was like,
"Yeah, okay. I will I will do it
someday." Right. F first person I I told
was my girlfriend. She was like, "Cool."
>> Yeah. She
>> does. She really think it's cool or is
she into this stuff?
>> She she's not into this stuff. She She
thinks it's it's pretty cool that I
found something, but um she really can't
um yeah see the the nerdy value of of
these kind of numbers.
>> Was this lowhanging fruit?
In the in the search for prestigious
primes, you said
>> Yes. Yes. You
you can think of numbers and primes as
like an orchard and not all trees are
equal and like the just the generic
prime tree. That's amazing. And everyone
wants to get the get the fruit off that
tree.
>> That's the magic far away
>> magic far away tree. Um but everyone's
cleared the branches. Like there's only
a little bit of fruit right at the top.
But then
>> there's an infinite amount of fruit.
There's an infinite amount of fruit
above the threshold. Correct. Correct.
It's a very generous tree in that
regard. But then there are other trees
with less appealing fruit that may be
lower down. And what you're going to do
is trade off the appealingness of the
fruit with the distance from the ground.
And I wouldn't say this was lowhanging
fruit. I'd say medium medium low, but
very cool type of number. I mean, we're
making a video about it. People are
finding numbers all the time and we
don't make a video. But this I was like,
that's cool. People wouldn't know about
that. and it was within reach of Stefan
just being an enthusiast putting some
code together and being able to to find
one. And what I really like about it
other than like it's a fun number and it
was an enthusiast who decided to give it
a go. It was a combination of
self-written code or be in C which is
far more efficient than Python not to
throw shade on Python um and the
shoulders of giants. So taking the
giants can reach further up the tree.
And so by taking the uh algorithms
already developed for other bits of
prime grid and applying them with their
own civ, Stephan was able to do this.
And that collaboration of prime grid
which is just like a huge collaborative
amount of human intellect gone into it
and a little lone warrior getting the
fruit. Great.
>> You really ran with that fruit analogy.
>> Thank you. I didn't realize I didn't
realize how much how much juice was
available in that analogy.
>> Show me the computer that did it.
It's that little one there. Is that
under the
>> Yeah, it's it's the mini computer with
like uh eight cores.
>> That's it. That's where the world's
largest reversible prime was found in
there.
>> Yeah.
>> Do you prefer calling them reversibles
or e-urpers?
>> I don't know. Um, I just stick with the
wording reversible.
>> Are there an infinite number of emers
according to Wikipedia? Open problem. We
don't know. This could be the final
e-urper.
Imagine. Wouldn't that be special? Now,
that would be top of the tree. We don't
know how big the tree is in this case.
This could be the last run. Isn't that
incredible? So, yeah. Uh, open problem.
You could try and find a bigger one or I
don't know if there's a way. There might
be some kind of statistical argument
about what percentage of primes, but if
it was that easy, someone would have
done the proof by now. There might be. I
don't know how hard that would be to be
honest. Again, a lot of lowhanging
proofs like that are done. And the fact
that Wikipedia says no one's managed to
prove one way or the other yet probably
means it's a slightly difficult proof to
be able to do. So, there you are. That's
possibly the final emote.
I reckon there's another one. Nah, I
think that's it. Here on number five, we
show you a lot of freakish cool things
in mathematics like biggest prime
numbers. But to make these discoveries,
you need the foundations. You need to
understand how mathematics works, how to
code, all that kind of stuff. And for
me, you know, it's been a long time
since I learned that back at high
school. And if you want to get those
skills or you want to get them back, a
really good place to go is today's
episode sponsor, Brilliant.
Brilliant is jam-packed with courses
that are highly interactive, engaging,
and frankly just good fun. You'll get
smarter with a smile on your face.
But the thing I find exciting is that
for some people, the skills and
knowledge they're taking on could lead
to new career paths, new opportunities.
It could be the start of something
really big. To learn for free on
Brilliant for a full 30 days, go to
brilliant.org/numberfile
or scan that QR code there on screen or
of course there'll be a link in the
description. Brilliant's also giving our
viewers 20% off an annual premium
subscription which will give you
unlimited daily access to everything on
their site and apply
new I guess and uh yeah with
with the with these kind of prime
numbers there is no software to see for
them so um I try with my limited
programming skills as as
Matt um says all the time it's like
terrible Python code In my case, it's
terrible CC